{"tossups": [{"question": "While attending a sermon by this leader, reformer Michael Servetus was arrested and later burned at the stake. The Huguenots of France were Protestants who followed the doctrine of this reformer who served as de facto head of the Council of Geneva. This man attacked Roman Catholics and outlined his belief in \u201cpredestination\u201d in the work <em>Institutes</em> <em>of the Christian Religion</em>. For ten points, name this Protestant reformer who fled France for Switzerland in 1536.", "answer": "John <b><u>Calvin</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Lyman Wilbur controversially gave this structure its name. The Mike O'Callaghan-Pat Tillman Memorial Bridge rerouted traffic that once passed over this structure on Highway 93. Tourists can visit this structure by taking Highway 11 for forty minutes southeast of Las Vegas. Building this structure caused Boulder Canyon to be flooded by the newly-created Lake Mead. For ten points, what dam along the Colorado River is named for the president who was in office from 1929 to 1933?", "answer": "<b><u>Hoover</u></b> Dam", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Failed speculation on this commodity from Peru led to the self-proclaimed Emperor Norton losing his fortune. A movement named for \u201cFive Pecks of [this commodity]\u201d began when Zhang Daoling claimed to see a vision in which he was commanded to build a \u201cnew state.\u201d Innovations in producing this crop, sometimes grown on terraces, caused the population growth of Song China. For ten points, name this food grown in paddies and often eaten in its grain form.", "answer": "<b><u>Rice</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "During this decade, Derek Jacobi portrayed a stuttering Roman emperor in the miniseries <em>I, Claudius</em>. Quincy Jones scored a smash-hit ABC miniseries in this decade based on a book about Alex Haley\u2019s ancestry titled <em>Roots</em>. Sixteen Emmy Award nominations were given, with only one winner for Costume Design, to a TV show based in and named for this decade. For ten points, in what decade did the first two <em>Godfather</em> films win Academy Awards for Best Picture?", "answer": "19<b><u>70</u></b>s", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "One story supporting the plausibility of an early Japanese version of this accomplishment concerns the plight of the Three Kichis [[KEE-chees]]. The Dorset culture accomplished this feat but had dissipated by at least 1500. Another group that accomplished this feat, the Thule [[THOO-lee]], were called <em>skraelings</em> by another group who accomplished this feat and established L\u2019Anse aux Meadows [[lahn-tsoh-meh-DOH]]. For ten points, name this accomplishment whose celebration has been renamed in some states to Indigenous Peoples Day from Columbus Day.", "answer": "<b><u>Discover</u></b>ing the <b><u>America</u></b>s (accept <b><u>discover</u></b>ing the <b><u>New World</u></b>; accept descriptive answers indicating new settlement in <b><u>America</u></b> or the <b><u>New World</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "One of these systems known as a \"village\" type originally developed in the town of Chilmark, Massachusetts. That system, which developed on the island of Martha's Vineyard, is now extinct but was used by nearly every resident of the area until the early 20th century. One of these systems which spontaneously arose among students at the <em>Villa Libertad</em> in Managua was first studied by linguist, Judy Shepard-Kegl. Thomas Gallaudet [[gah-low-DET]] created a university, for ten points, to support users of what languages, often used by deaf communities?", "answer": "<b><u>Sign language</u></b>s (accept specific <b><u>sign language</u></b>s; prompt on descriptive answers of languages used by the deaf)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Linguistics"}, {"question": "A century-long war which was fought over this resource ended when Louis-Hector de Calli\u00e8re [[kah-LYEHR]] negotiated the Great Peace of Montreal. The French-Canadian <em>coureurs des bois</em> [[kor-UHR day-BWAH]] were men who traded these goods with Native Americans. The Embargo Act forced John Jacob Astor to found a company named for this good and to create trading posts in the Pacific Northwest. For ten points, name this good often processed from the pelts of beavers.", "answer": "<b><u>Fur</u></b>s (accept beaver <b><u>pelt</u></b>s before mentioned; accept answers indicating animal <b><u>skin</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In a depiction of this battle, lithographers Currier & Ives sketched the death of Henry Clay, Jr. while he led the 2nd Kentucky Volunteers. During this battle, the Saint Patrick\u2019s Battalion, made up of Spanish-speaking Irish ex-pats, manned heavy batteries that were stormed by the 1st Dragoon regiment. This battle occurred in La Angostura, in the state of Coahuila [[kwah-HWEE-lah]]. For ten points, name this inconclusive battle between sides led by Zachary Taylor and Santa Anna during the Mexican-American War.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Buena Vista</u></b> (accept Battle of La <b><u>Angostura</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Music played by <em>lunera</em> [[loo-NEH-rah]] accompanied these people at some events before which these participants were usually massaged with oil. The greatest honor that these people could achieve was receiving a wooden sword known as a <em>Rudis</em>. The <em>Hoplomachus</em> [[hop-loh-MAHK-us]] and <em>Murmillo</em> [[muhr-MIH-loh]] were two specific types of these people who were trained at schools after being bought by a master. Including Spartacus and many rebels in the Third Servile War, for ten points, who were these enslaved competitive fighters of ancient Rome?", "answer": "<b><u>Gladiator</u></b>s (prompt on \u201cslaves\u201d)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "In 2016, this politician defeated Loretta Sanchez in one election following Sanchez's controversial remarks about Muslims. During the 2020 Democratic primary, this politician notably attacked Joe Biden for his opposition to bussing policies. Former Georgia Senator David Perdue drew criticism for allegedly intentionally mispronouncing this politician's first name. As a Senator, this politician was preceded in office by Barbara Boxer and succeeded by Alex Padilla. For ten points, name this U.S. vice president.", "answer": "Kamala <b><u>Harris</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "In 2012, this park's Curry Village tent city was linked to a hantavirus outbreak. The Ahwahneechee people were driven out of the region which is now this park after the Mariposa Wars. This park's Fallen Tunnel Tree is a giant sequoia that fell in 1969. Theodore Roosevelt gave federal protection to this park's region at the behest of John Muir [[MURE]]. During a trip to this park, Ansel Adams took iconic photographs of El Capitan and Halfdome. For ten points, name this American national park located in the Sierra Nevada Mountains of eastern California.", "answer": "<b><u>Yosemite</u></b> National Park", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "The Condor Legion, a detachment of this organization, was sent to aid Nationalist forces in the Spanish Civil War. Under Albert Kesselring, this organization conducted Operation Retribution, which resulted in the death of over 17 thousand Yugoslav civilians. On Adlertag, or Eagle Day, this organization lost nearly fifty aircraft while attempting to gain superiority over the British Royal Air Force. For ten points, name this military organization, the aerial warfare branch of the Nazi Wehrmacht.", "answer": "<b><u>Luftwaffe</u></b> (prompt on \u201cWehrmacht\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A 1946 Conference in this nation\u2019s capital was coordinated by \"Lucky\" Luciano to coordinate mob policies and discuss collective business interests. The U.S. refused to recognize this nation\u2019s government, which was led by Ram\u00f3n Grau, after he nullified the Platt Amendment. The explosion of the USS <em>Maine</em> off this nation\u2019s coast led to war between the U.S. and the Kingdom of Spain. The U.S. trained exiled men as paramilitaries to overthrow, for ten points, what nation\u2019s Castro government as part of the Bay of Pigs Incident?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Cuba</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The sparsely populated Chausey [[SHOW-ZEH]] Islands are the southernmost group of islands in this body of water. The two largest territories in this body of water are two semi-independent bailiwicks which claim sovereignty based on the \"constitution\" of King John. The 1120 White Ship disaster occurred during an attempt to cross this body of water. In 1875, Matthew Webb became the first person to swim across this body of water unaided.  For ten points, name this seaway which separates France from a namesake island nation.", "answer": "<b><u>English Channel</u></b> (prompt on \"The Channel\"; accept La <b><u>Manche</u></b> before  \"namesake\")", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "This person, who got himself intentionally court martialed out of West Point, published a book of poetry with works like \u201cTamerlane\u201d after a generous donation from his fellow cadets. The 1841 killing of the \u201cBeautiful Cigar Girl\u201d inspired this man's novel \"The Mystery of Marie Rog\u00eat\" [[ROH-ZHEH]] featuring detective C. Auguste Dupin. The tearing down of the historic but derelict Hezekiah House in Boston inspired this writer\u2019s story \u201cThe Fall of the House of Usher.\u201d For ten points, name this American author of \u201cThe Pit and the Pendulum\u201d and \u201cThe Raven.\u201d", "answer": "Edgar Allan <b><u>Poe</u> </b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "Prince Albert loaned his horses to model for a statue of this woman and her daughters now situated on Westminster Bridge. This woman's husband, Prasutagus [[prah-soo-TAY-gus]], willed half of his kingdom to his daughters and half to the emperor. The Roman Empire's gross mistreatment of this woman and her family led her to rebel against Governor Gaius Suetonius Paulinus and lead a tribal army across Britain to burn the city of Londinium. For ten points, name this woman, a modern folk hero and the historical queen of the Celtic Iceni [[eye-SEEN-ee]].", "answer": "<b><u>Boudica</u></b> (or <b><u>Boadicea</u></b>; or <b><u>Boudicea</u></b>; or <b><u>Buddug</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "Two tribes of these people clashed at the Battle of Hingakaka due to an inequitable distribution of kahawai fish. This group, which pursued a \"King Movement\" in the 1850s, used P\u0101 hillforts to defend from intertribal raids during their destructive Musket Wars. William Hobson negotiated the poorly-translated Treaty of Waitangi to give the British Crown dominion over this people\u2019s historic land on North Island. For ten points, name these indigenous people of New Zealand.", "answer": "<b><u>Maori</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In this state, an incident in which four police officers were killed by Robert Charles sparked deadly race riots in 1900. In 1873, Sheriff Christopher Columbus Nash orchestrated a massacre of Black militiamen in this state\u2019s Colfax massacre. Homer Plessy intentionally violated this state\u2019s Separate Car Act by sitting in a whites-only car headed to St. Tammany Parish, leading to a landmark U.S. Supreme Court case. For ten points, name this state whose diversity is exemplified by its Creole culture.", "answer": "<b><u>Louisiana</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>While jailed in Occitania, this man wrote \"No Man is Imprisoned,\" after which</u></b> <b><u>he was moved to Trifels Castle despite Pope Celestine II's threat of excommunication.</u></b> <b><u>This ruler was captured by Leopold of Austria for having killed Conrad of Montferrat</u></b> <b><u>[[monh-feh-RAH]] before being ransomed by (+)</u> Emperor Henry VI. This ruler died at Chalus-Chambrol [[shah-LOO shahm-BROHL]] after warring with his former friend and ally, Philip Augustus of France. The co-signer of the Treaty of Jaffa with (*) </b>Saladin, for ten points, who was this king of England during the Third Crusade?", "answer": "<b><u>Richard I</u></b> (or <b><u>Richard the Lionheart</u></b>ed; or <b><u>Richard, Coeur de Lion</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Future Baseball Commissioner Kennesaw Mountain Landis convicted a</u></b> <b><u>participant in this sport, Jack Johnson, for violating the Mann Act by transporting a</u></b> <b><u>white woman across state lines. A man who participated in this sport\u2019s \u201cBattle of the</u></b> <b><u>Century\u201d with (+)</u> Joe Louis had earlier refused Adolf Hitler\u2019s personal request to fire his Jewish promoter. Ferdinand Marcos hosted the \u201cThrilla in (*) </b>Manila,\u201d a bout in this sport between Joe Frazier and Muhammad Ali. The Marquess of Queensberry established the modern rules of, for ten points, which contact sport?", "answer": "<b><u>Box</u></b>ing", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Anita Snook trained this person, and Betty Klenck thought she heard this</u></b> <b><u>person ask her husband to take out a suitcase. Gerald Gallagher claimed to have</u></b> <b><u>found this person's sextant, and the Gardner hypothesis attempts to explain this</u></b> <b><u>person's (+)</u> fate. Navigator Fred Noonan worked with this person to fly a Lockheed Electra 10E. While flying to Howland Island from Lae [[LAY]], New Guinea, this person (*) </b>vanished over the Pacific Ocean. For ten points, name this aviation pioneer, the first woman to fly solo across the Atlantic Ocean.", "answer": "Amelia <b><u>Earhart</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The persecuted Hazaras minority group opposed this group by joining the</u></b> <b><u>Northern Alliance led by deposed president Burhanuddin Rabbani. This</u></b> <b><u>organization\u2019s leader, Mohammed Omar, ordered the destruction of the giant (+)</u></b> <b>Buddha statues of Bamiyan in 2001. This Sunni regime, which succeeded the Mujahideen, combined Pashtun cultural norms with a draconic interpretation of (*) </b>Sharia [[SHAH-REE-AH]] law. For ten points, name this fundamentalist group which controlled Afghanistan from 1996 until it was overthrown by the 2001 U.S. invasion.", "answer": "The <b><u>Taliban</u></b> (accept <b><u>Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan</u></b> or <b><u>IEA</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man attempted to annul his forty-year marriage to Louisa Frederici,</u></b> <b><u>falsely claiming that she tried to poison him twice. This man, who sometimes went by</u></b> <b><u>the native name Pahaska, served as a (+)</u> courier on the Pony Express at age fifteen. This man gained his sobriquet at age 22 after defeating William Comstock in a hunting contest while supplying (*) </b>meat for workers on the Kansas Pacific Railway. For ten points, name this showman who owned a namesake Wild West show which employed the likes of Annie Oakley and Sitting Bull.", "answer": "Buffalo Bill <b><u>Cody</u></b> (accept <b><u>Buffalo Bill</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A portion of one of these structures was built in Kicking Horse Pass on the</u></b> <b><u>border of Alberta and British Columbia. Construction of one of these structures was</u></b> <b><u>led by Sandford Fleming, and the Pacific Scandal involved the building of one of these</u></b> <b><u>structures.</u> </b><em><b><u>Navvies</u></b></em><b><u> [[NAH-vees]] and (*)</u> </b><em><b>coolies</b></em><b> helped build one of these structures for Canada for which Craigellachie [[kruh-GEH-luh-kee]] was the site of the last (*) </b>spike. The Canadian Pacific forms, for ten points, what type of structure which crosses North America?", "answer": "<b><u>Transcontinental Rail</u></b>road (prompt on \"Railroad,\" \"Train track,\" or similar answers; accept <b><u>Canadian Pacific</u></b> Rail or <b><u>CP</u></b>R before mentioned; prompt on \"railroad across Canada\" or similar answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This city's historical coat of arms depicts a white sheep carrying a golden cross</u></b> <b><u>with a flag attached. This city contains the longest continuously inhabited executive</u></b> <b><u>mansion in the Americas, La Fortaleza [[for-tah-LEH-zah]]. The most populous of this</u></b> <b><u>city's eighteen (+)</u> barrios is Santurce [[san-TUHR-say]]. This city's Castillo San Felipe del Morro successfully repelled a 1595 invasion attempt by Sir Francis Drake and is home to the Spanish-built fortress (*) </b>Castillo San Cristobal. For ten points, name this capital and largest city of Puerto Rico.", "answer": "<b><u>San Juan</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>In the aftermath of this event, Henry Garnet was killed for refusing to break</u></b> <b><u>the confidentiality of confession. Francis Tresham may have sent a letter to William</u></b> <b><u>Parker which revealed the plans for this event. The leaders of this event had earlier</u></b> <b><u>raided (+)</u> Warwick Castle, a move that led Richard Walsh to corner them at the Holbeche House. The perpetrators of this event hoped to usher in a Catholic state by putting Elizabeth (*) </b>Stuart on the throne. James I was targeted in, for ten points, what plot in which Guy Fawkes attempted to blow up the House of Lords?", "answer": "<b><u>Gunpowder</u></b> Treason Plot (accept the <b><u>Jesuit Treason</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Emile Edde [[eh-MEEL eh-DEE]] served as president of this country in which</u></b> <b><u>Galo Plaza and Odd Bull, members of the UN Group of Three, were dispatched. Robert</u></b> <b><u>Daniel Murphy was sent to this country, allowing for the election of Fouad (+)</u> Chehab [[foo-WAHD she-HAHB]]. Dwight Eisenhower aided this country's leader, Camille Chamoun [[shah-MOON]], in Operation Blue Bat. Comprised largely of (*) </b>Druze, Maronite Christians, and Muslims, for ten points, what is this country in which the U.S. occupied Beirut?", "answer": "<b><u>Lebanon</u></b> (accept <b><u>Lebanese</u></b> Republic)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}